hello everyone it's june 23 2022
and we are
in week eight
of the textbook group cohort one
we're
starting chapter
and we'll be continuing the chapter 4
next week
we're more than halfway
done
with the time
and with the
chapters that we're going through in the
first half of the book
so let's go to
chapter four and just raise your hand
and gather or write in the chat if you
have anything that you want to address
so the
i'm going first to the math overviews
page where i've written some overviews
for the previous chapters
of varying levels of completeness but
this
is very important as we set off into
chapter 4.
so on page 64.
this chapter is more technical than
chapters one through three appealing to
linear algebra differentiation and a
taylor series expansion
those readers interested in the details
may turn to the appendices appendages
those who do not want to delve into the
theoretical underpinnings may skip this
chapter
so
keep that in mind as we continue on
and
it can be an area of discussion and
learning and such
but let's approach these
themes and formalisms
with the
authors forewarning
that this is
something we can
look for more detail in the appendixes
as well as
skip this chapter
even if we
might disagree of course
okay
any other
overall comments on chapter four
just for whomever
read it even a part of it what was there
overall perspective on chapter four what
was it trying to do
what approach did they take
yeah ali and then anyone else
i think if we take uh the materials in
chapters one two through three as uh the
foundational materials on which
uh the active inference theory uh
is supposed to build uh well this
chapter four is uh one of the first
steps uh
toward uh building the actual uh theory
and uh
i mean going beyond just the basics of
foundational materials so using the tool
the tools and foundations uh established
in previous chapters
we are now
uh perhaps ready to tackle the problem
of
actually constructing the generative
models in uh two different
in two different situations as discrete
time
models and as continuous one
awesome thanks
yes
in the chapters
page
we can recall back to
chapter 1
that just laid out the structure of the
book
chapter 2 provided the low road to
active inference
which began with bayesian inference
and talked about a few
other prerequisite or preliminary themes
including introducing
variational and expected free energy
as
imperatives
in the sense that they're
able to be bounding surprise
chapter three introduced the high road
to active inference which was starting
not from the
mechanistic kind of nucleus of the bayes
equation but rather from the imperative
for survival and persistence
also introducing in a first pass the
markov blanket
concept and partitioning
chapter four is indeed when we start to
get into
many details that were not
covered in
earlier sections
it's gonna
first begin by bringing us
closer to this connection between
bayesian inference and the free energy
evaluation
and then the central idea of a
generative model
is discussed
that is going to be described in
discrete time
specifically using the pomdp formalism
partially observable markov decision
process
and then
as well as in continuous time
then there's going to be some
very interesting figures and formalisms
and discussions on
what generative models underlie
predictive coding
and motor reflexes which is moving us
towards chapter five
which is going to have some empirical
work mainly cited out
and some discussion on the plausible
neurobiologies
that can be implementing or modeled as
implementing or modeled with
the kinds of generative models of which
have been
prepared for in chapters two and three
motivated in chapters two and three
really
and then described
in their essence in chapter four
also just a reminder that
in the math group activities but we're
all in the math group we're all in this
learning journey together we've been
striving to make the natural language
descriptions
for equations
so
that would be extremely extremely
helpful
every annotation that people can make
is helpful people shouldn't feel abashed
or ashamed to make any kind of
contribution it can always be
re-ordered or edited by others but
this is how we're going to create those
like natural language descriptions of
equations and ask questions about them
even just
copying and pasting what does this mean
what does this mean they're all
helpful contributions
because this is
very
technical
and
it's not immediately apparent how
for example
these copious equations in chapter 4
relate to some of the broader
discussions from the earlier chapters
but look at that
okay
if anyone
has
more questions to add
they can do that or if they want to
upvote questions feel free to do that
it's motivating for other people when
they see that their questions are like
being improved or other people are
paying attention to their questions
so that's always something free and
helpful that people can engage in
um are beliefs policy or state
if the person who asked it is here they
can feel free to address it
because it's a very short
partially formed
question
i also wasn't sure whether this was
using the cad cad ontology
which uses policy and state in a
slightly different way
but
beliefs in a general sense
coming from the bayesian ontology
are referring to any
distributional expression
bayesian beliefs
those are
states
policies in the actin phontology
which you can just mouse over and find
out
it's a sequence of actions
and policies are constructed or
enumerated
by
the affordances the e
vector
that the generative model has
over a given time horizon
so if it's able to go left to right over
two time steps all the policies are left
left left right right right right left
um
does anyone else just want to add
anything else to this short
question
otherwise it's a fine clarifying
okay
in the discussion of active inference in
pomdps
the authors write
to update beliefs about policies
we find the posterior that minimizes the
free energy
does the posterior at time t
become a prior at time t plus one
what does anyone think
i guess it depends on the
um
specific posterior and prior because
that can
mean multiple things but in the context
of figure 4.3
i'd say it does
because we are updating our prior which
becomes at the end of a time step
becomes the posterior probability
which then is fed back as the prior
thanks totally agree with that uh there
needs to be an initiating prior
d
which is shown with a three here
in the discrete time
and that is like the initial prior
and then
prior and posterior are referring to
what incoming data
so after the data at
point one comes in
the updated posterior
is now playing the functional role of
the prior for the next data point coming
in
okay then here's sort of a related
question
well
we've addressed this
question in the narrow sense but
it would be very
helpful to look through
the order in which different topics are
addressed in chapter four
because
these are um
some questions that are invoking things
that are much later
and
we don't assume that people have um
[Music]
high or low comprehension of this
chapter yet
but many of these questions
it's really important that we understand
like why we're bringing them up so let's
just walk through very quickly
the chapter to see why they're bringing
up things in a different order
in terms of looking at the figures in
formalism
4.1
is returning to bayes
and
uh i think this is a really nice
representation
here's the joint distribution of x and y
the hidden states and the observables
and it's like it gets split up
into
y condition.x and x
so this is like the probability the
joint distribution of the coin flip and
the die
is
the distribution of the coin flip
conditioned upon the die and the die
itself
so it's just separating out a joint
distribution
and that's the heart of bayes theorem
this is a key move to move an
integration problem
a sum in the discrete case or an
integration problem in the continuous
case into an optimization problem
which permits incremental
solutions of improving quality unlike an
integration problem
which
you might just be tallying up numbers
and not necessarily moving closer
to knowing when you're done with that
integral
they introduced jensen's uh inequality
which is the log of the average is
always greater or equal to the average
of a log
and that's true for any
shape that has this kind of a
curve anything where there's a
decreasing curve
and here's where that gets applied
above
we had
this
taking this joint distribution
multi multiplying it by an arbitrary
distribution divided by itself
so that's one
whatever q is
later q will play a more specific role
and then
here
the expectation is inside the log
here the expectation is over the log
itself
so
the one that we'd really want
would be
like the joint distribution
um
would be like the expectation
of the joint distribution
divided by some
function q
jensen's inequality
allows us to
make this
uh instead of
an equal sign make it a greater than an
equal sign
and then pull the expectation out
and utilize that
as the negative free energy
which is going to be bounding us
on this one that we would truly want
but going about it
by using this
um
nice feature of the natural log
base theorem in the logarithmic form
anyone can totally raise their hand and
add
details
allows rearrangement
into this form
which is already recalling
the free energy that we saw from
variational free energy from from
equation 2.5
more details to be filled in and that's
why we want to be annotating these
equations and so on
generative models is the name of this
chapter
to calculate free energy we need three
things data variational distribution
family and a generative model which at
minimum is composing of the prior and
likelihood
they're going to be describing two
different kinds of generative models
this is a really nice and intuitive
graphic
for those who might have
different familiarity with statistical
representations
the circles are random variables
and the squares are probability
distributions describing relationships
these are some
bayes graphs
that are simpler
and less action-involved
than
this
canonical octave representation where pi
is policy
and so
uh yayakaburo um three is the b matrix
yes it is
there's like
three these threes are the b matrix
but this is the d
letter
so
i i agree though
um
sorry which one is the d letter
the first three
yeah
because they're playing similar roles
but they're a little bit i mean or what
do you think about that
yeah i guess
i mean i was thinking about it as this
being just one snapshot of
like an infinite um
factor graph so
i mean just the fact that it's um
assigned the p of s tau plus one given s
tau and pi
uh i i understand what you mean by um by
saying that it's kind of like it plays
the
role um
yeah i'm not i'm not entirely sure
though
look we'll come back to this because
there's actually a few other interesting
notes
um
so this is kind of the simplest
uh of the
graphs that they describe
this is like one variable influencing
another variable
this is like two
factors z and x influencing y
so
two
is like a
little factory
that outputs y conditioned upon the
state of x and z
so
knowing
this notation
and how to read these directed
graphs
is
relatively essential for interpreting
more complex graphs that involve actions
and so on
here's x
as like a upstream hidden cause
that influences two downstream variables
that don't influence each other
and here is like
a hierarchical model where v influences
x and x influences y
does anyone have like thoughts or
questions about this
this is a graphical probabilistic model
the variables are stochastic or they're
statistical random variables
and it's a graph it's consisting of
nodes and edges
4.3 is going to
introduce these two basic forms of the
generative model dynamic through time
used in active
in the factor graph form
does anyone want to describe what they
see in this figure
the top is in the discrete time case
s
is the hidden state
temperature of the room
o are the observations the thermometer
readings
the two
is the relationship between
the temperature in the room and the
readings of the thermometer
three
is how the temperature is changing
through time
and then it is just like jakob said it's
kind of like here we can think of this
as being like a little bit of a snippet
from this infinite sequence
of temperatures through time
but
in practice
there has to be an initiating prior
pi
are
policies
policies are sequences of actions
sequences of affordances that are
concatenated over some time horizon
that's what we're evaluating like
expected free energy on
and
policies
represent causal impact in the world
and we can look at this graph which is
why this is an important
prerequisite to understand
because the way in which policies
influence the worlds isn't like by
taking the temperature and like just
changing it to a different value
it's changing
three which is how the temperature
changes through time
any thoughts on the discrete time
formalism
yes mike
so as represented in this figure
the policy is not changing over time is
that correct
the set of policies
in this figure
is not changing
it's not that it can't this is just
only showing
two steps of
some policy being applied yeah just the
way it is in this figure so if
if we were to maybe extend this figure
um
with
two more of the the bottom section we
could also extend policy and have that
changing over time and feeding into that
yes and that's actually one of the
amazing and interesting things about
this graphical representation
is we can say okay well let's carry out
this s to five more time steps
and then let's have
pi one implemented here and then let's
have a do pi two here
and it's kind of like if you can draw it
you can do it
and that's very
important work from devry's and fristen
and par
from around five years ago
was demonstrating that
if the bayes graph
can be drawn
that there's a forney factor graph
representation
and where there's the 40 factor graph
there's
a attractable variational message
passing approximation
i don't know exactly what the guide
rails are for like are there graphs that
can't
be amenable to message passing and etc
but just at a first pass
four
graphs that look
like this
they can be
drawn and more variables can be added
and so on so it's kind of like a visual
code
for probabilistic graphical models
so maybe that's a fun exercise is like
to think about
causal inference in our
day
like the temperature in my room is being
influenced by like
whether the air conditioner is running
in the other room and the temperature
outside
which one of these scenarios does it
model onto
and just kind of
taking scenarios that are
familiar to us and then separating them
in terms of
how are the hidden states changing
through time what are the observations
what policies influence how hidden
states change their time
but
this is going to be
an interesting different
view on the bottom here with the
continuous time model
does anyone want to describe the
continuous time
variant
also one interesting
piece here is in the live streams that
we just did over the last few weeks 46
they make it clear distinguishing
between dai decision active inference
and mai motor active inference
and beyond just modeling cognitive
decision making versus motor reflex arcs
they also highlight how the dai is a
discrete type model that's using the
pomdp
while the motor models tended to use
continuous time
so
they're laying out
and
also kind of generalizing
to show the similarities
between these two different variants
and we can use the notation concordance
table
to like highlight some of those
parallels
this is where the taylor series
approximation comes in and the
generalized coordinates of motion though
they can also be applied to the discrete
time
here
we have we have um
x
x prime and x double prime
the prime notation indicates temporal
derivatives and second derivatives
if anyone has a thought on that feel
free because this is not
doing time series prediction
in the same way that the pomdp is
the pomdp
is
in the memory of the program
there's a value at the previous state
the current state and the next state and
however many other states in the time
horizon
way that a continuous time
taylor series approximation is dealing
with reduction of uncertainty about
future data
is quite different than the way that
these discrete time models are doing so
what's happening here
is
the the value of the function at
now
is being
estimated or provided
then
the first derivative is calculated
so here
three has the same structure but whereas
this is the hidden state at the next
time point
conditioned upon the hidden state at
this time point and the policy
here's
the derivative of x
conditioned upon x and the policy
v
v also has a slightly different
interpretation because it's not
sequence of events either
and analogously for the second
derivative and the higher derivatives
so they're still emitting observations
but these are not observations at future
time points in the same way
and that
is visualized
in this box 4.2
so here is x of t
at time t so this is like the way that
the time series is going to go
x of t
is just this value here you know 5.
the first
term being added in the taylor series
expansion
is the first derivative
rate of change at that x zero
that's giving you a better approximation
through time
then the second derivative adds this
quadratic feature
and so taylor series
converge
closer and closer
moving further and further away from the
target points
as they include higher and higher
derivatives but there isn't
and
um
there isn't an explicit calculation
in the taylor series
of like let's just say this is like you
know one two three
time steps
it's not like well what is
gonna happen at three time steps from
now
the taylor series could then be plugged
in with three
to calculate that
however
this is not um
calculating
x x prime x double prime at t equals
three
it's calculating it for x sub zero
and then using this expansion
[Music]
to
achieve reduction of uncertainty of more
and more distal points
so that's quite interesting
and it's again it's an extremely
different way of doing time series
prediction
in the continuous time framework
than this kind of explicit consideration
of past present future
state values
okay any other thoughts on 4.3
because this is one of the most key
figures
but
the things we can explore and ask ali
uh about this figure on page 69 it says
the relationship between a state and its
temporal derivative here depends on
slowly varying causes
uh nu uh uh i just want to to make sure
uh does this mean
this slowly varying causes uh here is
used uh
to account for the fluctuations or it
has
some different meaning
yes slowly varying causes
so
policies
are influencing the causal unfolding
of states
in this discrete formalization
here
in the continuous time setting
the very the cause slowly varying causes
more slowly than
these changes
play a similar role to policies above
so these are
these causes intervene in how the
derivatives are calculated
uh no i mean uh here
in the discrete time uh well obviously
uh we have uh
we can say stable policies uh that
doesn't uh
that don't change through time but uh in
the continuous time
uh well
i don't know at least that was my
understanding that uh the policies can
slightly change
uh
but the change can be some somewhat
somehow negligible and uh well that's
because of the the additional uh term uh
for fluctuations in the equations uh and
uh they don't necessarily uh affect uh
the main
the main the components of the equations
one could set it up so that
the policies are ineffectual
so that the state changes through time
are
with their own endogenous dynamics not
influenced by policy
or one could imagine a situation where
the states don't change it all through
time and their changes are entirely
driven by policy and i think analogously
there could be a setting
in which the derivative of x
is hardly influenced by these v
slowly varying causes
or v might
entirely describe
the derivatives of x
but i'm not sure if just at this level
of generality
we can
allocate importance
to kind of the endogenous dynamics or
like sort of the policy independent
changes
just the way that those
states are changing or analogously
derivatives are calculated
but that's a great question um lyle and
then mike
yeah this might be just slightly off
topic but
the tools
if you if you're using a multi-mode
simulation tool
then
it can handle both
in some sense it's going to try and
solve both continuous formulations and
discrete time formulations so one they
would typically call
agent based and the other would be
ode-based or something like that
just
the way that they do that is a little
bit of sleight of hand because of course
they're not solving the equations per se
they're estimating the solutions
and they always if you have that then if
you have a slowly
changing set of parameters like you
might model with the discrete case
then
then you
you know you've got a uh
an event q and those events are however
far apart they need to be
then to estimate the continuous form
they simply set that delta t delta t
goes to zero
in some says never goes in the software
exactly to zero but then you you
compress that delta t down to very small
time slices
and then you have estimated your
continuous form
and so by
by doing that you can really have
a pretty
comprehensive way to represent both
cases in the same
modeling environment so
yes
great point um numerical approximations
to continuous processes can be done
through
breaking them down into discrete
processes
and then making sure that as your delta
t is getting smaller and smaller
that you're getting a convergent
estimator
the approach that's taken analytically
here
is to use a taylor series approximation
mike
and so in thinking about how we should
build the mental model of the taylor
series approximation or incorporate that
in our model um that's one example of
how you might capture the time series
structure
and you could potentially substitute in
other approaches to maybe capture finer
detail or
discrete events that might occur on the
series
like what
uh like uh
lois decomposition or something like
that where you're taking apart
components of the time series things
like trend seasonality um discrete
events
yes i think the analytical comparisons
would be um
tight or loose but kalman filter
generalized bayesian filtering
splines
uh time series decomposition
these are all in the category or like in
the genre
of this
ollie
uh by the way
thanks uh for the clarification that was
really helpful uh uh
well uh to ask my question uh more
explicitly uh on page 78 uh
equation 4.15
we have
uh
some additional omega
terms
which are defined as
stochastic fluctuations my question was
that
is the term slightly varying
uh
somehow related to these stochastic
fluctuations or not
yes i believe that the slowly varying
is in relationship to it being included
with the flow
component
rather than with the um at that time
scale
stochastic
more thermal like vibration
and that was explored in like live
stream 45
with free energy principle made simpler
but not too simple
um
with this
idea of
the length of n
and how physics and mechanics are
predicated upon the separation into
flow-like actions
at a given scale
and then stochastic
non-flow aligned
changes
and the path of least action is when
the the the limit of the
the stochastic term going to zero
but let's let's come there um
yeah as people can see even though it's
like we could totally read this like 20
times
and it still is like
why is the next word there why is the
next equation there but okay
they're introducing these two
types of generative models
that have like kind of tantalizing
isomorphisms but also very interesting
differences
they're going to first focus on the
discrete time
the partially observable markov decision
process
formalism is used someone asked like why
is the categorical notation used it just
allows it it makes it easy to look at a
matrix and to interpret the matrix as
like a confusion matrix not just a
matrix that is confusing like they can
be but one that has to do with like a
coin flip
so categorical outcomes
um
[Music]
the uh three nodes
are the transition function
here in the categorical context
between different states
that's this b
and here's where we see the d
the prior over the initial state
and b
and together these account for the three
nodes in figure 4.3
they play a functionally similar role
here's where they get distinguished
selecting between models of behavior
and that was another question which
maybe we could get to um
[Music]
requires
selection amongst these categorically
discrete plans
and then
the softmax
normalizes
and ensures that the probability over
those policies is normalized so that
they can be understood
as a probability distribution
okay a categorical probability
distribution
here's the expected free energy
that we've seen before
more
on
expected free energy
specifically on how this kl divergence
term which as we talked about last week
was about
how
the preferred states
are realized
active inference uses f and g
they're related but they play different
roles
vfe f
is the primary quantity minimized over
time
that was interesting to read because
efe
is what is minimized prospectively
through time
whereas here the claim is that
variational free energy is what is
minimized over time
in relationship to generative model
so
again more more could be explored there
they're going to focus on a
rearrangement of equation 2.6 here
with the ambiguity and risk
being juxtaposed with the informational
value information gain infomax
and pragmatic value
they then
move
into the
linear algebraic form
where the bolds
okay
i don't know if bold is used in the same
way in this
appendix
as it is in these equations
does anyone
know about what bold means here it could
mean the vector
ali
yes i also think uh bold the
most probably means vector matrix
yes
it it gets pretty subtle though
sometimes because there's times where
there's italics bold and neutral being
used
uh very closely
um it's like it's when they're used
closely it can be confusing and then
when they're used not closely it's hard
to juxtapose
so
um
more
expected free energy rewriting
within the linear algebraic
form
softmax
bringing back the logs
variational inference rests upon
factorization that's related to the
sparsity of the bayes graph moritz
hey uh so just going to 410 again um i
was wondering what's the use of the
categorical distribution here because
like
maybe i miss it but it's not really
explained in the text
what what they use it for like there's
one sentence saying like oh yeah uh
the fifth line shows that the prior
belief about observation is a
categorical distribution
like what is it for what does it do i i
i've never seen it before
i don't know if it has to be categorical
i like a preference distribution could
be a continuous
function
but here
um
[Music]
it's
just
simpler
perhaps to show it as a categorical
like there's two outcomes having the
food and not having the food
so then that's a categorical
distribution of preferences and of
observations
so they're just modeling a situation
where there's categorical
differences
that are being preferred
as opposed to like
a preference over some continuous
distribution
does that
address it they're just modeling a
situation where there's a cont where
there's a categorical difference
with observations and with preferences
just because like
mathematically it's easier now to to
start with that or like
yeah i think didactically it's a lot
clearer because you can see like a two
by two matrix
did i observe the food or not
did i get the food or not
instead of like a distribution of
temperature
preference
and a distribution of observations
i'd expect that the formalism will work
out the same in the sense that you're
still minimizing your surprisal
and you're still performing distribution
matching
but also
this is like a distribution matching in
a categorical context that has an
interpretation of almost like false
positive and false negative
all right okay i will go with it thank
you for the explanation
yeah it's a it's a good question
and i mean
yeah
it
the the matrices
help connect to the linear algebra
and the matlab
representations
and also just to like sort of
match or no match like in 46 the example
had to do with like wanting ice cream
and then they observed ice cream or not
okay
pmdp and also like where does this eta
we'll we'll come back to the another
time but just to kind of get through it
all the first pass
um more details on a pomdp
s and v
auxiliary variable
i don't think this is the v
here
because we're in the pomdp setting
so it's just an auxiliary variable used
as sort of a
analytical convenience
that concludes their discussion of the
discrete time
model
into continuous time but first they
describe again markov blankets
and take kind of a second pass
the blankets are the causes of x
upstream which are parents
and the children
and the parents of the children the kind
of co-influencers
of course there's more to
say but that's what the um pearl
definition is
how that gets mapped to sense and action
states and what influences what what's
in the blanket on the blanket etc
those are model specific
and then here are two common
um
message passing schemes that are used
for approximate inference
unless the base graph is fully connected
there is a markov partitioning
here this is pretty funny nb no te penne
good note good note to note
the slightly non-standard use of the
expectation operator perhaps by
overloading it
with a massive subscript
but it's unclear what
exactly they meant there
is
showing alignment between these two
different schemes but there's definitely
citations to go into more into detail on
like belief propagation and message
passing inactive
and then we see several of these
um
figures
personally
i think it's slightly challenging to
understand whether this is being used
illustratively
or whether these specific topologies
are as directly interpretable
as these topologies are
but here we see kind of
if you uh blur your eyes
here's policy at the top
here's the observations
here's time minus one
here's s minus t minus one
t and t plus one
so we can see
some
resonances
with 4.3
but now we're in the continuous time
motor active inference from 46
is justifying the use of continuous time
based upon the um continuous unrolling
aspect of sensory input and motor output
they're going to start in a different
place than they did with the po mdp
model
in this case
we have much more of a physics
grounding
again check out live stream number 45
to see about the langven and how this is
connected
but this is a much more physics based
grounding
in terms of like a flow
operator and a stochastic term at a
given time scale
the um
stochastic
term
is
assumed to have a normal distribution
and that kind of relates like what mike
said about de-trending
like one can think of this stochastic
term
as being what happens when you've
de-trended all of the signal that's
non-gaussian out
you're left with like the residuals
which have a gaussian
uh
nature
precision is capital pi
and that's the inverse of the
fluctuation
and so that's they're going to connect
that to the common filtering
here we return again to the generalized
coordinates motion
um
coming from this taylor series
approximation
route
so if somebody said i have 10 numbers
and we need to predict 10 years in the
future
the discrete time way would be like well
let's try to predict it at each of those
10 years
and that those will be your 10 numbers
the generalized coordinates of motions
approach
which we explored the most in
livestream number 26
with decosta
at all
in bayesian mechanics
the 10 numbers could be like
the value today
and the derivative today the second
derivative and the third and the fourth
and the fifth up however many that's the
generalized coordinates of motion
so it's like a snapshot
of the process and all of its higher
derivatives and so the generalized
coordinates of motion are very similar
to taylor series approximations
in how they represent centered at a
certain point x naught
how one expects
as movement happens away from that x
naught
reducing surprise and so here is like
x with a um dot on top is the change in
x and then this is like the derivative
of the change in x and so on
here the tilde notation is used for the
generalized coordinates of motion
so we see this
equation
which was just for one
value
like
where you are on the freeway you know
and then this is the generalized
coordinates of motion
the free energy is written down
for
this
generalized coordinates of motion
with precision
here
the closest that we came to exploring it
was in 43
on predictive coding
there's some more details on gaussian
the relationship between like gaussian
uh processes
and uh
also i think lyle brought up this um
like sort of
mode
and multi-mode simulations
this is modeling a single mode
not that it can't model a bimodal
distribution
but
this is where the laplace approximation
comes into play
this is potentially even unnecessarily
complex
but it's there
and the
laplace approximation
is fitting
um a quadratic
distribution
that tracks
the mode
so like the the highest point
on the distribution
and then it fits
a parabola around that
here
is more details on the hierarchical
nature
and the kind of multi-time scale nature
that's implied
um
ultimately by the lengthen
and then
there's uh
it'd be good to juxtapose figure four
six and four
four to see how they're similar and
different
but here we see message passing
happening on the generalized predictive
coding architecture
and that was like explored a lot more
not with this exact figure but this was
explored more from like an analytical
and empirical perspective in 43.
then
there's an abrupt ending
but the following chapters are going to
appeal to the formalisms
and apply them
so any
thoughts or ideas on chapter four as we
close out
and hopefully next week we can have um
a lot of questions and things like that
even basic questions it's like if the if
you read it and you understood it
then it'd be awesome to contribute a
question
that would explore someone else's
understanding
or
prompt towards how you thought about it
in a way that made sense for you
and if you don't understand it
then just ask the question
ali and then anyone else
i just wanted to briefly mention an
additional point related to
the question about
the reason behind
using the categorical distribution
on page 74
it says uh
the fifth line shows that the prior
belief about the observations is the
categorical distribution whose
sufficient statistics are given in the c
vector i think here sufficient
statistics is the key term uh to
understand the reason behind using
categorical distributions because uh for
sufficient insufficient statistics
we don't
necessarily use the exact
the exact modeling or distributions
instead we use a substituted statistics
that is simple enough to calculate and
also
close enough to the uh to the actual
data so
i think
that can help
in understanding the reason behind that
decision
good point
and
this is definitely a
a technical
note but um is it fair to say that like
the mean and the variance are sufficient
statistics for a gaussian distribution
uh yes i think so
so like
that's one of the
perhaps proximate mechanisms by which
the laplace approximation and
variational inference more generally
are able to
deal with arbitrary true distributions
by fitting
a family of distributions that have
um tractable optimization structure
and a vastly reduced set of sufficient
statistics
if you had even just a simple bimodal
distribution while there would be like
the location of the two peaks the
relative heights of the two peaks the
skewedness and all the you can have many
many parameters needed to describe it
in contrast the laplace approximation
only requires the location of the mode
and the variance estimate
and so
where that's adequate
it's simple and fast
where it's inadequate
you'll at least know
because you'll continue to be surprised
at new observations coming in
okay any final comments on this
chapter four part one
definitely a challenging
though interesting
chapter
and it really is at the heart of
active
and as we hopefully explored a little
bit today it includes like basic
intuition pumps
as well as
some rosetta stone like representations
and many many
equations
which i hope we can unpack
so could someone explain it in simple
words
it's what we've been asking for every
single equation
and it's something that everyone can
contribute to
all right well
looking forward to people's
edits over the coming week and
editions
and uh
we'll come back in
one week for part two on four